Hyalen Moreira Caldeira

Portfolios: Main Portfolio & Under Construction

Phone: +1 (909) 234 7007 - Dublin, OH Email: <u>hyalen@gmail.com</u>

LinkedIn: https://www.linkedin.com/in/hyalen
GitHub: https://github.com/hyalen-caldeira

ABOUT

A **Software Engineer** with 8+ years of experience, I have **Software Development** (**Python**, **Java/Spring**, **Angular**), **DevOps/SRE** and **Cloud** experience. I enjoy developing software from the ground up, learning new technologies, refactoring legacy code and ensuring the satisfaction of the companies I work for. With an open-mind and a drive to learn, my goal in life is to develop software that will advance humanity as well as inspire the next generation of programmers.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Accenture – as a Full Stack Engineering Manager

Columbus/OH, March 2019 - Current

- → Bank Client (in partnership with an Entertainment Company) As a Integration Specialist & Data Engineer
- Developed SAP CAP applications deployed on SAP BTP leveraging event-driven architecture to respond dynamically to real-time
 events and business triggers. The application was responsible for analyzing data available in folders, enabling efficient data ingestion,
 transformation, and integration with downstream systems;
- Wrote Python scripts to perform complex data transformations and processing logic within the ETL pipeline; Leveraged Python libraries such as Pandas, NumPy, PySpark for efficient data manipulation and analysis;
- Developed ETL pipelines using AWS Glue to extract data from various sources, transform it according to business requirements, and load it into target destinations; Implemented data cataloging and schema inference features of AWS Glue for metadata management and schema evolution;
- Created AWS Lambda functions to execute specific tasks within the ETL pipeline, such as data validation, enrichment and
 aggregation; Orchestrated Lambda Functions as part of serverless workflows for parallel processing and scalability;
- Designed and implemented workflows using AWS Step Functions to coordinate the execution of individual ETL steps, including
 Lambda functions and Glue Jobs; Defined state transitions and error handling mechanisms within Step Functions to ensure robust
 and fault-tolerant ETL processes.

→ Insurance Client – As a SRE (Site Reliability Engineer) & Full Stack Engineer

- Designed and developed an auto-healing application using Java/Spring Boot and Angular, eliminating manual tasks associated with
 error detection and resolution through specific API access. The application is fully customizable, enabling users to add new
 functionalities based on detected errors;
- Created dashboards on *Grafana* to monitor the overall system health, including metrics such as CPU/Memory utilization, *Kubernetes* PODs restarts, system peak utilization within a specified time range, error rates, among other parameters;
- Monitored Azure EKS for Kubernetes issues, performed scaling adjustments for deployments as needed, updated Kubernetes
 deployment configurations to better address the system's requirements.;
- Oversaw deployment processes and promptly address any issues that arose during the monitoring phase. Terraform, Helm and
 Kubernetes maintenance. Utilized Splunk queries, Grafana dashboards and Camunda for comprehensive system monitoring;
- Integrated monitoring solutions using *Prometheus* to track system performance and detect issues.

→ International Food Chain Client – As a DevOps Engineer

- Utilized Terraform to provision and manage AWS resources in a reproducible and automated manner;
- Defined infrastructure configurations as code, ensuring consistency and version control;
- Established and maintained *CI/CD* pipelines for automated building, testing, and deployment of applications. Integrated version control systems, such as *Git*, with *GitLab CI*;
- Integrated monitoring solutions with Prometheus to track system performance and detect issues;
- Implemented centralized logging systems such as ELK Stack (Elasticsearch, Grafana, Splunk) for efficient log analysis;
- Implemented/configured AWS EKS (Elastic Kubernetes Service) auto-scaling features to dynamically adjust resources based on demand.; Utilized AWS Cost Explorer or similar tools to optimize resource allocation and reduce costs.

cFive – as a Senior Software Engineer

Laguna Hills/CA, June 2018 – March 2019

Spring Security SAML, Java/Spring Boot — Designed, architected and developed a security model (Microservice Architecture) to allow access to the LA County main system using Microsoft AAD/MIM. The system is accessed by government departments such as the FBI, Police Department, among others. This project is an implementation of a SAML 2.0 Service Provider, completely built on Spring Framework. A web solution devised for Federated Authentication by integrating Spring Boot and Spring Security SAML. The configuration has been completely defined using Java annotations (no XML).

Conversant – as a Software Engineer

Westlake Village/CA, June 2017 - January 2018

- Java, Spring Boot, RESTful APIs and Hibernate Write code in an Agile environment for an online Ad Network company's Java API.
 Add server-side support for new SaaS UI features, address bug tickets in legacy system with focus on TDD and delivered quality projects that have been well-received;
- Spring Cloud Implemented from scratch a central config server where all configurable parameters of applications are written
 version controlled. The benefit of a central config server is that if we change a property for an app, it can reflect that on the fly
 without redeploying the app. The solution maintains all properties of all environments (development, staging and production), and if
 any properties are changed, it will pick up the changes and reflect them without an application rebuild or restart;
- Hazelcast and Spring AOP Implemented a distributed cache to lock correlated services being treated at the same time among different servers.

ACADEMIC QUALIFICATIONS

- CKAD Certified Kubernetes Application Developer;
- HashCorp Certified Terraform Associate;
- <u>AWS</u> Certified <u>SysOps</u> Administrator;
- AWS Certified Developer Associate;
- CFCD Cloud Foundry Certified Developer;
- React (by Udacity), San Francisco CA 2017.
- Course: Software Engineering 2004/03 to 2005/08
 University: Universidade Federal de Minas Gerais Brazil
- Course: Technology in Data Processing Brazil, 2000
 University: Centro Universitário UNA

TECHNICAL SKILLS

- Proficient in: Java/Spring; Familiar with: Python, Angular, TypeScript;
- Interest: Full Stack Development, SAP BTP, SAP CAP, Machine Learning, Generative AI;
- AWS: IAM, EKS, VPC, EC2, S3, Lambda, API Gateway, CodeCommit, CodeBuild, CodePipeline, CloudFormation, Elastic Beanstalk, DynamoDB, CloudWatch, EventBridge, StepFunction and others
- Architecture/Standards: Microservices, Micro-Frontend, Design Patterns, OOP, object and data modeling;
- Test Tools: JUnit, Karate, Groovy/Spock, Selenium, Jasmine/Karma; Data Interchange: JSON, XML;
- Paradigms: Agile, SCRUM/XP, TDD, CI/CD processes, DDD (Domain Driven Design);
- Others: Kubernetes, Terraform, Helm, Istio, Ansible, Git, Splunk, Grafana, Prometheus, Camunda BPMN, SAP BTP, SAP CAP, SAP PI/PO, Gradle, Maven, NoSQL, Relational Database (Oracle/MySQL/PostgreSQL), Docker, Stash, Bamboo, Jenkins, Nexus, Swagger, Tomcat, Jersey, jQuery, HTML5, CSS3, Bootstrap, Linux/UNIX, JSP/Servlet.